<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
  <!--Info Block for Updates and general info-->
<elements>
    <info>
        <name>Circle of the Swiftness Druid</name>
        <update version="1.0">
            <file name="Circle_of_the_Swiftness.xml" url="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/Pandablockhead/DnD5e-Aurora-Builder/refs/heads/main/Circle_of_the_Swiftness.xml" />
        </update>
    </info>

  <!--Content-Type,Description and Rule-Set-->
  <element name="Circle of the Swiftness" type="Archetype" source="Homebrew: Fools Gold" id="ID_HOMEBREW_SUB_CLASS_CIRCLE_OF_THE_SWIFTNESS">
      <supports>Druid Circle</supports>
      <description>
          <p>The Circle of Swiftness was an ancient order of druids that was thought to be lost to time until a powerful druid named Gothi, the last surviving member of this circle, shared its teachings with other druids of Ambria and slowly revived the circle’s popularity. The circle’s teachings aim to deepen a druid’s bond with an animal companion by fighting together as one to protect the balance of nature.</p>
          <div element="ID_HOMEBREW_FEATURE_COMPANION_MOUNT" />
          <div element="ID_HOMEBREW_FEATURE_TWIN_BEAST_SHAPE" />
          <div element="ID_HOMEBREW_FEATURE_COMPANION_CASTING" />
          <div element="ID_HOMEBREW_FEATURE_ENTWINED_EVOLUTION" />
          <div element="ID_HOMEBREW_FEATURE_BEAST_STRIDE" />
      </description>
      <rules>
          <grant type="Archetype Feature" id="ID_HOMEBREW_FEATURE_COMPANION_MOUNT" level="2" />
          <grant type="Archetype Feature" id="ID_HOMEBREW_FEATURE_TWIN_BEAST_SHAPE" level="2" />
          <grant type="Archetype Feature" id="ID_HOMEBREW_FEATURE_COMPANION_CASTING" level="6" />
          <grant type="Archetype Feature" id="ID_HOMEBREW_FEATURE_ENTWINED_EVOLUTION" level="10" />
          <grant type="Archetype Feature" id="ID_HOMEBREW_FEATURE_BEAST_STRIDE" level="14" />      
      </rules>
  </element>

  <!--Companion Mount Feature-->
  <element name="Companion Mount" type="Archetype Feature" source="Homebrew: Fools Gold" id="ID_HOMEBREW_FEATURE_COMPANION_MOUNT">
      <description>
          <p><em>2nd-level Companion Mount feature</em></p>
			    <p>You form a bond with a wild beast that becomes your companion mount. Your mount can take the form of any beast, but it uses the companion mount stat block, possibly altering its physical characteristics beyond the norms for a creature of its kind.</p>
			    <p class="indent"><strong><em>Allies.</em></strong> Your mount is friendly to you and your companions, and it has its own distinct personality.</p>
			    <p class="indent"><strong><em>Initiative.</em></strong> Shares your initiative count and takes its turn directly after yours.</p>
			    <p class="indent"><strong><em>Combat Actions.</em></strong> It can only take the Dodge action and move, <em>unless</em> you use your <strong>bonus action</strong> to command it to take a different action, such as attacking, hiding, or interacting with an object.</p>
			    <p class="indent"><strong><em>Incapacitation.</em></strong> If you are incapacitated it can take any action of its choice, not just Dodge.</p>
			    <p class="indent"><strong><em>Movement.</em></strong> As part of your movement each turn, you can spend half your movement speed to either mount or dismount your mount. While you are mounted, your companion mount acts on the same turn in initiative as you and can only move unless you direct it to take another action. You fall off your mount if you are incapacitated or knocked prone.</p>
			    <p class="indent"><strong><em>Attack Redirection.</em></strong> you can redirect any attacks made against your mount to target you instead, and you can use your reaction to grant your mount advantage on Strength and Dexterity saving throws. Your mount can make death saving throws.</p>
          <p class="indent"><strong><em>Mount Death.</em></strong> If your mount dies, you can bond with a new companion mount by performing an 8-hour ritual to commune with the spirit of another beast. Mounts can also be resurrected using magic such as revivify or Resurrection.</p>
          <p class="indent"><strong><em>Notes for Resurrection.</em></strong> Cant have more than one companion mount.If you form a bond with a new companion mount, your bond with your current companion mount is broken.</p>
      </description>
  <sheet><description>
          <p>You form a bond with a wild beast that becomes your companion mount.</p>
          <p>The Mount has the following features:</p>
    			<ul>
              <li>
              <em>Allies</em> - Your mount is friendly to you and your companions, and it has its own distinct personality
              </li>
              <li>Initiative - Shares your initiative count and takes its turn directly after yours
              </li>
              <li>Combat Actions - default actions are dodge and move, for everything else you need to use your bonus action to command it
              </li>
              <li>Incapacitation - If you are incapacitated it can take any action of its choice, not just Dodge
              </li>
              <li>Movement - can use half your movement each to mount or dismount, while mounted your turns act as one and you can only move, unless you use your bonus action for a command, fall off mount if incapacitated or knocked prone
              </li>
              <li>Attack Redirection - you can redirect attacks at your mount to yourself, with your reaction you can grant it advantage on STR and DEX saving throws, mount also can make death saves
              </li>
              <li>Mount Death - on mount death you can revive it with revivify or Resurrection, alternatively perform 8-hour ritual to bond with a new one
              </li>
              <li>Notes on Resurrection - Cant have more than one companion mount.If you form a bond with a new companion mount, your bond with your current companion mount is broken
              </li>
          </ul>
</description></sheet></element>

  <!--Twin Beast Shape Feature-->
  <element name="Twin Beast Shape" type="Archetype Feature" source="Homebrew: Fools Gold" id="ID_HOMEBREW_FEATURE_TWIN_BEAST_SHAPE">
      <description>
          <p><em>2nd-level Twin Beast Shape feature</em></p>
          <p>Your bond with your companion mount allows you to wild shape into a form that matches it, using the same statistics as your companion mount. When you wild shape in this way, you ignore the CR restrictions of the Beast Shapes table.</p>
      </description>
  <sheet><description>
      <p>Your bond with your companion mount allows you to wild shape into a form that matches it, using the same statistics as your companion mount.When you wild shape in this way, you ignore the CR restrictions of the Beast Shapes table.</p>
  </description></sheet></element>

  <!--Companion Casting Feature-->
  <element name="Companion Casting" type="Archetype Feature" source="Homebrew: Fools Gold" id="ID_HOMEBREW_FEATURE_COMPANION_CASTING">
      <description>
          <p><em>6th-level Companion Casting feature</em></p>
          <p>Your magic flows through your companion like a raging river.</p>
			    <p class="indent"><strong><em>Attack Properties.</em></strong> Your companion mount’s attacks become magical for the purpose of overcoming resistance or immunity to nonmagical attacks and damage.</p>
			    <p class="indent"><strong><em>Channel through Mount.</em></strong> While you are within 100 feet of your companion mount, you gain the ability to channel any spells you cast through them, treating your mount as the point of origin for purposes of determining your spell’s range.</p>
			    <p class="indent"><strong><em>Self-Casts.</em></strong> When you are affected by a spell with a range of self, as long as you are mounted on your companion mount, you are both targeted by the spell.</p>
      </description>
  <sheet><description>
          <p>Your magic flows through your companion like a raging river.</p>
          <p>Gain following features:</p>
    			<ul>
              <li>
              Attack Properties - mount attacks are magical to overcome resistances and immunities
              </li>
              <li>Channel through Mount - if within of 100 feet range of mount you can cast spells from their location
              </li>
              <li>Self-Casts - if you are affected by a spell with range of self, both the mount and yourself get targeted
              </li>
          </ul>
  </description></sheet></element>

  <!--Entwined Evolution Feature-->
  <element name="Entwined Evolution" type="Archetype Feature" source="Homebrew: Fools Gold" id="ID_HOMEBREW_FEATURE_ENTWINED_EVOLUTION">
      <description>
          <p><em>10th-level Entwined Evolution feature</em></p>
          <p>You and your companion mount learn new secrets from nature.</p>
          <p>Choose one of the following traits to add to your companion mount’s stat block:</p>
          <p class="indent"><strong><em>Bond of Brambles.</em></strong> While the mount is within 5 feet of you and you are mounted on it or have assumed its form using Twin Beast Shape, terrain within 10 feet of your mount grows thick grasping brambles. Creatures hostile to you and your companions treat the brambles as difficult terrain and take 1d4 piercing damage for every 5 feet they travel within the brambles.</p>
			    <p class="indent"><strong><em>Swift Skies, Swift Seas.</em></strong> Your mount gains either a flying or swimming speed of 50 feet. You also gain this fly or swim speed when using your Twin Beast Shape.</p>
			    <p class="indent"><strong><em>Twin Tactics.</em></strong> Your mount has advantage on attacks against creatures within 5 feet of you while you are mounted on it or have assumed its form using Twin Beast Shape. You have advantage on attacks made against creatures within 5 feet of your mount while you have assumed its form using Twin Beast Shape. Neither you nor your mount can use this feature if the other is incapacitated.</p>
      </description>
  <sheet><description>
          <p>You and your companion mount learn new secrets from nature.</p>
          <p>Choose one of the following traits to add to your companion mount’s stat block:</p>
  			  <ul>
              <li>
              Bond of Brambles - if mounted or twin shaped change terrain in 10 feet radius enemies take 1d4 piercing dmg for each 5 feet they move in the terrain
              </li>
              <li>Swift Skies, Swift Seas - mount and you, if twin shaped, gain either flying or swimming speed of 50 feet
              </li>
              <li>Twin Tactics - if mounted or twin shaped and in less than 5 feet distance to mount it gains advantage on attacks, you gain this bonus aswell when youre twin shaped. if either of you is incapacitated it doesnt work
              </li>
          </ul>
  </description></sheet></element>

  <!--Beast Stride Feature-->
  <element name="Beast Stride" type="Archetype Feature" source="Homebrew: Fools Gold" id="ID_HOMEBREW_FEATURE_BEAST_STRIDE">
      <description>
          <p><em>14th-level Beast Stride feature</em></p>
            <p>The bond between you and your mount is exceptionally strong, intertwining your souls.</p>
          <p>Gain the following features:</p>
			    <p class="indent"><strong><em>Telepathy.</em></strong> While you are within 1 mile of each other, you can communicate telepathically with each other.</p>
			    <p class="indent"><strong><em>Teleportation.</em></strong> While your mount is within 600 feet of you, you can teleport onto its back or have it teleport to your side as a bonus action. Once you’ve used this ability, you can’t use it again until you finish a short or long rest.</p>
      </description>
  <sheet><description>
          <p>The bond between you and your mount is exceptionally strong, intertwining your souls.</p>
          <p>Gain the following features:</p>
          <ul>
              <li>
              Telepathy - telepathic communication within 1 mile radius
              </li>
              <li>Teleportation - Bonus action: teleport onto mountback / teleport mount to your side as if within 600 feet range
              </li>
          </ul>
  </description></sheet></element>
</elements>
